BSD is still dying.
Welcome to ""BSD is Still Dying.""
It’s not quite dead yet,
but we're getting there.
Well, welcome to the closing of the DCBSDCon
2009.
So, what is BSD?
Well, BSD is a derivative of UNIX.
Okay, so what is UNIX?
UNIX is an operating system.
What’s an operating system?
An operating system is the soul of a computer.
But, what’s a computer?
A computer is a tool, it’s basically a glorified calculator
that enables users to accomplish tasks better.
So, what is a user?
A user is someone who operates the computer.
It tends to stand upright, sort of like me
and Bob.
So, who am I?
My name is Jason Dixon.
First and foremost, I’m a Sysadmin.
I like to work on networks and firewalls.
I like to tweak;
no...
yes.
I'm a programmer, sort of.
I enjoy programming with Perl, PostgreSQL,
and Apache Web servers.
I'm a consultant here.
I'm an employee--
damn, not there!
Missed that slide, sorry, er, I'm sorry, OmniTI.
You can tell I switch jobs entirely too often.
And I'm a lover
of BSD.
Okay, but why am I here?
To talk about why
BSD is dying.
Sex...
and greed.
Ok, it really has nothing to do with either of these.
But if I told you licensing of blobs,
would you have shown up? Not that you had a choice.
To quickly summarize, what is BSD?
What is UNIX?
What is an operating system?
What is a computer?
A computer: A computer is a device that computes
especially, a programmable electronic machine
that performs high speed mathematical
or logical operations,
or that assembles, stores, correlates, or otherwise processes
information.
This is a computer.
This is a small computer.
This is a big computer
This is a big,
fake computer.
And this is a really old computer.
Well, what does a computer really do?
It helps us write documents.
For example, Linux man pages.
We can compose shopping lists.
Computers can even delete documents on the fly.
We can write emails,
surf the Web,
watch movies, uhh...
movies,
listen to our favorite music,
and even play games.
But how does the computer let us do these things?
It starts by taking text known as source code,
and using the compiler can translate it into binary
machine language.
That’s the foundation
for the kernel,
libraries,
and userland applications, otherwise known as
an operating system.
Like, BSD. So you ask:
What is a kernel?
It's a wonderful thing.
It allows for the management
of processes, memory,
and peripheral devices.
And by extension, it allows us to do cool stuff like
networking,
provide better security,
work with disks and file systems, create user interfaces,
interact with userland applications that let us
do things like
write documents, read email, surf the Web,
watch movies,
listen to music,
play games,
and much, much more.
In summary,
BSD is a UNIX-derived operating system that enables
users to harness the power of
a computer and process information better.
It uses a kernel to manage processes, memory,
and peripheral devices, and by extension
We can perform networking, enforce security,
read from and write to storage devices and interface visually to applications
like text editors
mail clients, Web browsers, multimedia players, and games.
For a second, I'd like to look back
on the history of UNIX for a few minutes.
Now, to be honest,
Kirk McKusick just trumped everything I had
from my talk.
So, a lot of this is gonna be a repeat,
but it's still pretty good.
So, in the beginning,
and yes, there was life before UNIX.
We had the Holy Trinity:
MIT, Bell Labs and GE teamed to create
a system called Multics,
the Multiplexed Information and Computing Service.
We have a huge GE650 mainframe running Multics.
You can tell the engineers from the pointy-haired bosses.
And so, it was a huge success.
We all run Multics on a laptop, mainframes, of course.
Actually, no, it was a commercial failure.
Fortunately there was a computer scientist at Bell Labs
named Ken Thompson.
He’d worked on the Multics project and was inspired
by the interactive computing
it provided.
Unfortunately, scrapping the Multics project
meant that he no longer had a system with which
to perform serious work like
Space Travel,
A space simulation game
He had written for Multics on the
GE 650 mainframe.
With Dennis Ritchie’s assistance
and his experience from the Multics project,
they were able to craft together an operating system
of assembly language
running on a PDP-7.
It was capable of interactive
computing with a terminal
rather than just feeding in
punched keycards.
They termed it the UNIX systems.
UNIX system, short for Uniplexed Information
and Computing System,
A play on the Multics name.
It's supported a number of users...
Did I miss something?
It supported a number of users...
Talk about your anticlimactic slides.
By 1970,
it officially became known as U-N-I-X
probably to save a byte of memory.
They would have made really good
OpenBSD programmers back then.
By 1971, the UNIX System was officially
put into production use.
It had been ported to the PDP-11.
It was capable of text processing
for the purpose of filing patents.
I was trying to visualize software patents
and a cat kicking a dog is probably
the closest thing to it in real life.
By 1973,
they rewrote UNIX
in a portable language created by Dennis Ritchie.
The C programming language evolved from the B language
adding data types and structures.
Thanks to a 1958 antitrust case, AT&T had been
forbidden to enter the computer business.
This meant UNIX could not be turned into a product,
so they would ship tapes
and disk packs of the source code
to anyone who asked.
Since the source code was freely available
and ran in a portable computer language
universities and research labs worldwide were able to run
UNIX on their own systems.
By 1974,
Professor Bob Fabry
at the University of Cal Berkeley
purchased a copy of UNIX for $99
for their own PDP-11
By 1977,
Bill Jolitz, a graduate student of Cal Berkeley,
distributed the Berkeley Software Distribution
otherwise known as
1BSD.
It included a Pascal compiler,
the ex editor,
and the ex editor.
By 1978,
2BSD had been released
which added the vi editor
and a C shell.
I'm definitely not old school when it comes to editors.
Corn Shell for the win.
1979,
3BSD was released,
adding support for the VAX platform.
It was coined as Virtual VAX or VMUNIX
thanks to the new virtual memory implementation
written specifically for the VAX UNIX/32V
computer at Berkeley.
Thanks to the success of 3BSD
the Defense Advanced Research Project Agency (DARPA)
ordered Berkeley CSRG with a contract to enhance UNIX
for the VLSI project.
These enhancements were
eventually released
as 4BSD.
Which added job control for the C shell
delivermail, the predecessor to sendmail,
the curses programming library,
and reliable signals.
Unfortunately, 4BSD was criticized for bad
performance on the VAX platform,
so Bill Jolitz went back to work tuning the kernel
to outperform VMS on the VAX
eventually releasing 4.1BSD for these performance fixes.
Two years later,
4.2 was released
incorporating a TCP/IP stack from BBN Technologies,
also a contractor for DARPA,
as well as the Berkeley Fast File System,
written by a dapper young man by the name of Kirk McKusick,
who was also kind enough to give us the original BSD mascot.
In 1986,
4.3BSD was unleashed
incorporating numerous performance improvements,
including a non-BBN version of the TCP/IP stack,
which was found to be superior by DARPA.
1998,
the next version of BSD was released.
4.3BSD-Tahoe, so named for the short-lived
Power 6/32 “Tahoe” platform.
This was an initial attempt of moving away
from the VAX platform.
Although the Tahoe was unsuccessful, it helped introduce
machine-independent code that would improve
BSD's future portability.
Up to this point, all versions of BSD
included proprietary AT&T code .
It required licenses from AT&T for their use.
These licenses have become prohibitively expensive,
driving demand for an AT&T-free version of UNIX.
This led to the release of Net/1
a BSD license distribution of the FreeBSD networking code,
unencumbered by any AT&T code or licenses.
The next year,
4.3BSD-Reno
was released.
The name suggesting
a gamble when used production use.
Regardless, it included the MACH virtual memory
system,
Sun-compatible NFS,
and continued the movement toward POSIX compliance.
It became apparent that the AT&T code was a
hassle, so Keith Bostic at the CSRG
re-wrote virtually all of the utilities and code that was
still from AT&T.
In the middle of 1991
Net/2 was released,
a nearly complete BSD UNIX system that was freely
distributable under the BSD license.
Net/2 was the basis for two separate ports
of BSD to the Intel 80386 architecture.
Bill Jolitz started the 386BSD distribution,
which became the basis for the 3BSD and
NetBSD projects.
Berkeley Software Design (BSDI)
came out with BSD/386,
a proprietary version later renamed as BSD/OS.
In 1992,
a wholly-owned subsidiary of AT&T,
UNIX System Laboratories,
also known as USL,
filed suit against BSDI claiming that AT&T’s
proprietary code was included in
the BSD UNIX product.
An injunction was filed asking for BSDI
to discontinue their use of advertising
which alluded to the UNIX name
own by AT&T, and supposedly aimed
to confuse unsuspecting users
or buyers
regardless of the fact that the BSD sold
for $995,
a 99% discount over AT&T's System V UNIX
which retailed for one hundred to
two hundred thousand dollars.
You can see why the average consumer might
get confused.
After an extensive analysis, it was
determined that the BSD/OS
was little more than Net/2, peppered with six files from Bill
Jolitz’s 386BSD.
The judge presiding over the case
denied the injunction
forcing USL to narrow their complaint
to recent copyrights
and a possibility of the loss of trade secrets.
The judge also recommended that the case be
heard at a state court before filing in a federal court.
So, taking this hint from the judge
they ran out to California,
refiled as quickly as possible (the University of Cal Berkeley)
to take any action-- to prevent--
it resulted that if USL wanted to take any action
against university and state courts,
it would be forced to do so in California
rather than their home state of New Jersey.
Soon after the filing in state court,
USL was bought from AT&T by Novell.
By 1994, a settlement had been reached in private.
The exact details of the settlement were unknown
until in 2004 when a California
public records law
allowed the details to be released
where they were published on the Groklaw site.
Details of the settlement included
these, and I think we've covered this in
Kirk’s talk, so we won't need to
iterate over those.
In hindsight, this confirmed our suspicions
of USL’s fate.
In June of 1994,
two BSD distributions were released
4.4BSD-Encumbered
was a version of BSD with AT&T code.
It was only available to AT&T licensees.
4.4BSD-Lite was also released which
contained no AT&T code.
It would become the new basis for a re-sync of the
FreeBSD and NetBSD source code trees.
As I mentioned, 4.4BSD-Lite
became the new baseline from which all the BSD
distributions would be based.
FreeBSD, one of the first,
and probably the most popular of the modern BSD
distributions (bite my tongue),
has a historically been focused on the Intel
x86 platform
and Linux and Windows markets.
Nevertheless,
FreeBSD has been been ported to other platforms,
including Intel x86, Itanium,
AMD64, DEC Alpha
PowerPC, and Sun UltraSPARC.
Some of the more popular features include
application jails, access controls,
excellent networking, SMP performance,
and more recently, ports of Solaris features
like ZFS and dtrace.
NetBSD,
which was also originally derived
from Jolitz’s 386BSD,
is typically known for portability to a wide range of
hardware platforms.
NetBSD has been ported to over 50 hardware platforms,
and kitchen appliances.
OpenBSD!
(No bias at all.)
OpenBSD is yet another modern BSD derivative,
originally forked from NetBSD 1.0.
It's known for being highly secure
with an emphasis on code correctness
proper documentation and truly open
and free source code.
Their mantra is ""secure by default.""
This philosophy has influenced in countless other free
and proprietary operating systems which now follow
their example.
Here are some of the more popular platforms
that OpenBSD has been ported to.
And although OpenBSD has numerous security enhancements,
we make efforts to integrate these changes into the
base system as native, transparent technologies.
The philosophy has proven much more effective
than ""bolt-on"" technology such as SELinux,
where the onus is placed on the Systems Administrator
and is quite often disabled.
I'm being generous.
You see, here are
some of the features in OpenBSD.
They have a consistent release schedule with new releases
available around the first of May and November.
DragonFly, another BSD,
started by Matt Dillon in 2003.
It's a logical continuation of FreeBSD 4.8.
He started the DragonFly BSD project
when his vision for threading in SMP conflicted
with the other developers working on FreeBSD 5.
They continued work on their SMP revamp
(which, I think, is probably complete by now),
as well as the other lightweight
kernel threads implementation.
More modern goals are focused on supporting
generic clustering support natively in the kernel,
and features like the HammerFS.
MAC OS X is an operating system
sold by Apple
which runs on both PowerPC and Intel platforms.
Alright, hecklers.
Darwin is the heart of OS X,
a full capable BSD UNIX derivative,
with enhancements brought in to make OS X
a true consumer-friendly operating system.
Unfortunately, it's still somewhat of a hybrid,
merging the Mach kernel from NeXTSTEP
along with various userland pieces
from FreeBSD.
Some other BSD distributions including
Tru64 UNIX from DEC
then Compaq, then HP.
Now we've covered some of the history behind BSD,
I like to address the real shortcomings
of modern day BSD.
0:18:00.960,0:18:3.980
So, why is BSD dying?
That's what we're here to uncover.
First and foremost,
because IDC says so.
Market share is at an all-time low,
under 1%.
And of course,
Netcraft confirms these findings.
BSD came in last place
in a SysAdmin networking test.
I don’t recall which of the BSDs were tested, but it's
probably safe to assume they all finished dead last.
Market leaders and pundits have predicted that
open-source software can't make money.
If we continue to give away free software, how
will we finance our developers?
Analysts are forecasting a slow spiral into bankruptcy.
It's a little dated, but man, you just got to love this guy.
BSD... Bad!
As a community,
BSD has had a surprising inability to
adapt.
As we can see by this graph...
As we can see by this graph, the number of
ASP pages served per hour
on Windows servers far outnumber those
on Linux and all the BSDs.
Linux actually did generate some.
We have to presume it's because of obfuscation.
Renaming their files ASP.
Of course, a significant loss of talent.
FreeBSD has lost 93% of their core
developers.
It's assumed that most of these have jumped ship
to DragonFly BSD.
Unfortunately, since none of the BSDs share code,
they usually have to start from scratch all over again
tracing the project’s roots from 4.5BSD-lite.
Fortunately, not all is lost.
There's still a handful of very small companies
still using BSD today.
I know you probably haven’t heard of most of these.
This is my employer!
Yay, OmniTI.
Hopefully, the successes seen at--
yes, the lawers actually told me
I had to put that on there--
hopefully the successes seen in these isolated industries
will bubble up into the mainstream.
Looking forward, there's a number of challenges
ahead of us to ensure the BSD survives
generations of future geeks.
The challenges aren’t simply of the technological
nature,
but include a number of political and legal
obstacles as well.
First and foremost, virtualization is on everybody’s
radar.
Products like Xen, QEMU, VMware, and Parallels
allow us to optimize our resources running BSD.
All this means I can run over 100,000 instances of NetBSD
on a server with four gigs of memory/
It also means I have to hire 1,000
NetBSD systems administrators
to manage that one server.
Not only is this a miserable return of investment,
I don’t think there are over a thousand NetBSD users out there.
We're looking for more advanced file systems
to handle the current performance limits
associated with high capacity multi-tier byte arrays.
Ports of Solaris ZFS have already been completed
in part to FreeBSD 7 and MAC OS X
They have blobs, NDA’s,
and closed documentation all go hand in hand.
These are political challenges that threaten
to limit hardware availability to BSD developers
and end users.
Projects like Linux, and even FreeBSD
had casually signed
agreements and NDA’s to accept non-free binary
drivers into the source tree.
These arrangements work against the spirit
of free software,
and open-source software, all for the purposes
of short-term gains
like 3D eye-candy and rotating desktops.
This coming the guy who set up a
game server in the next room.
Within the last year or so, legal challenges have surfaced.
Linux developers have blatantly stolen BSD licensed code,
replacing the license notification with GPL
and any of their copyrights where no work was done.
Beyond the legal ramifications of these actions,
this demonstrate a lack of respect
and cooperation for their free
software peers.
Diversity in the BSD is a healthy trend.
It promotes new features and competition
in the intellectual market
resulting in better systems for all of us.
In the end, diversity can bring unity throughout our community.
And with unity,
a common goal.
The end.